原视频名：Analyzing Video Footage Of Collapse of Massive Arecibo Telescope
原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/59WQIRvezzI
原视频发布日期：20201204
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
Today the National Science Foundation had a press conference
今天(美国)国家科学基金会(NSF)开了一个新闻发布会
where they revealed footage of the collapse of the large facility at Arecibo
透露了阿雷西博大型设施倒塌的画面
and well I'm I really kind of want to talk my way through all of this.
而我真的很想以我的方式来谈谈这些
This is a camera down in the control room
这是控制室里的相机
just showing how the whole thing went down literally.
展示了整个设施坠落的场景
That was footage by Carlos Perez who set up a gopro to record this just in case this happened.
这是Carlos Perez用Gopro拍摄的画面 拍摄时就预计这有可能发生
It's important to realize there were observatory staff on site when this happened.
重要的是要意识到 当事情发生时 现场有天文台的工作人员
They were working in the safe areas as much as possible
他们尽可能地在安全区域工作
but it wasn't without risk and we are very happy to hear that nobody was injured during this collapse.
但也不是没有风险的 而我们很高兴地得知在这次坍塌中没有人受伤
I'm going to come back to this video but I want to look at the second video
我待会再讲回这个视频 但我想看看第二个视频
which is taken from a drone which was inspecting cables on tower 4.
这是从正在检查4号塔线缆的无人机上拍摄的
The drone was being operated by Adrian who was one of the technicians on site
无人机是由Adrian操作的 他是现场的技术人员之一
and the drone would have been sitting like right there when things started to go wrong.
而这架无人机就差不多一直呆在那儿 直到问题开始出现
And I've never seen a cable failure so close.
而我从来没有在这么近的距离见识到线缆故障
Remember these are three inch steel cables which are carrying hundreds of tons of load.
记住 这些三英寸的钢缆承受着数百吨的负载
It happens really fast.
啪的一下 很快啊
The center cable has a small break then it pulls itself out of the socket.
先是中间的线缆有一点断裂 然后就从插座中拉了出来
Then the other cables start failing.
接着其他线缆开始失效
The cable supporting the line feed is the last one to go.
支持(信号)馈线的线缆最后才断裂的
The drone then turns around and we get to see the platform falling into the side of the dish.
之后 无人机转过来 我们就能看到平台掉进了碟型天线的侧面
We get missing material falling down.
我们可以看到缺损的材料正掉落下来
And yeah everything is over in less than 30 seconds.
是的 一切都在不到30秒的时间里结束了
I mean there's still debris fluttering down and dust settling
我是指还有碎片和尘埃在落下
but you can see the massive scars left in the dish and the debris that has been smashed on the mountainside.
但你可以看到碟型天线里留下的巨大伤痕 还有砸在山坡上的碎片
I don't want to turn this video into rubbernecking disaster images
我不想把这段视频变成吸引眼球的灾难影像
but I've had a lot of people ask me to talk about this and talk about the dynamics
但已经有很多人要我谈谈这件事 还有这其中的力学问题
and where it can go from here.
还有就是阿雷西博望远镜的未来
But before I dive back into frame by frame analysis of the demise of this,
但在我深入分析这样一帧帧的衰败之前
let's just take a look at what it once was.
让我们来看看它曾经的样子吧
In its prime this glorious monument to science, able to look back to some of the earliest parts of the universe
这座光荣的科学纪念碑在它的鼎盛时期 能够回溯到宇宙最早的部分
and also look at some of our closest neighbors in ways that other instruments could not,
并以其他仪器无法做到的方式来观察我们的一些近邻
the Arecibo telescope is truly a unique instrument.
阿雷西博望远镜真的是一个独特的仪器
And yes there is a bigger radio telescope but it doesn't do radar.
是的 还有一个更大的射电望远镜(指FAST) 但它不能进行雷达天文的工作
It doesn't have the same wavelength limits.
它的工作频率也和阿雷西博不一样
But of course that's me cherry-picking the things that Arecibo did very very well.
但当然 这只是我在选择性地吹捧阿雷西博的长处
This is of course I say Arecibo.
当然我会这么说阿雷西博
What we're really meaning is the 305 meter dish at Arecibo.
我想说的是 阿雷西博的305米碟型天线
There are other instruments on site but this is clearly the most prominent one.
尽管阿雷西博不仅仅是这个天线 但这是最突出的
And I believe that it should be visible from space with the naked eye if where to look.
而且我相信 如果在太空中用肉眼找准位置看的话 应该是可以看到的
So let's talk about that footage.
那么我们来谈谈那段录像
Why was there a drone there?
为什么会有一架无人机在那里？
They were using drones to inspect the cables.
这是因为他们用无人机来检查线缆
In fact they had been very actively inspecting the cables
事实上 他们一直在积极检查线缆
because they knew the cables were going to break soon
因为他们知道线缆很快就会断掉
and there's a web page here that catalogs individual strands observed breaking inside these large thick cables.
而有个网页记录了观察到的粗大线缆中断裂的每根钢丝
These are before and after photos and you can see the paint popping off and wires popping out.
这些是断裂前后的照片 你可以看到油漆弹开 钢丝弹出
These are bundled together strands of hundreds of steel wires.
每根线缆都是由数百根钢丝捆绑而成
They need to be bundled so that they're flexible.
捆绑起来才有弹性
And as they break they break one strand at a time.
而在断裂的时候 一般一次只断一根
So at the start of the drone shot you can see three cables hanging onto the top of tower number four.
那么在无人机影像的一开始 你可以看到三根线缆挂在四号塔的顶部
The three lower cables are the primary cables that were used to support the platform.
下方的三根线缆是用来支撑平台的主要线缆
These date from the 1960s.
这些都是上世纪60年代制造的
The cable above is part of the cable system that supports the catwalk and the waveguide.
上面的线缆是支撑天桥和波导的线缆系统的一部分
There are supposed to be four primary cables.
本来应该有四根主缆
But the fourth one broke in november which ultimately led to this collapse.
但是第四根在11月断裂了 最终导致了这次的坍塌事件
But if you look on the saddle there are a bunch of wire sticking out of the top.
但如果你看一下这个电缆鞍座 上面有一串钢丝伸出来
These are the remains of that fourth cable that broke.
这些就是第四根断裂的线缆的残骸
And if you're wondering what that black strap is. That's connecting two cables.
那条黑色的带子是用来连接两条线缆的
That's part of a pully system(?) which was used to lower the socket from the first cable that failed.
那是拉力系统的一部分 用来降低第一根线缆断裂处的插座(位置)
It just slipped out of its socket rather than snapping.
它只是从插座上滑落下来 而不是断掉了
So the other two support cables were attached to a structure that was added in the 1990s.
那么另外两根支撑线缆被连接到90年代添加的结构上
so this is a frame from later in the video and one of them is missing because that's the one that fell out.
所以这是视频后部分的一帧画面 其中一根支撑线缆没了 因为那根脱落了
But the one nearest us you can see hanging down there that's after the tension has been dropped on.
但离我们最近的那条你可以看到还挂在那里 这是拍摄在拉力释放掉之后的时间
So that's where those cables are attached.
那么这就是那些线缆连接的地方
Watch for them when things start moving.
当事情开始发生的时候要看着他们
Okay so now the video is playing at one quarter speed
好了 现在视频正在以四分之一的速度播放
and the cable to watch is the one in the middle the one the lower one with the black strap around it.
要注意的是中间 靠下的那根有黑色带子的线
Now you'll see it's lost a lot of paint that is because the wires have been snapping inside the cable.
那么你会发现它掉了很多油漆 那是因为线缆内的钢丝断裂了
And every time they do that they just knock the paint off the exterior.
每次有钢丝断裂时 都会打掉了外部的油漆
So there's going to be a single break.
那么接下来就会有一根线缆断裂
And when a single wire breaks the other ones shift a little to take up the load.
当一根线缆断裂时 其他线缆就会移动一下 以承担起负载
And so there's a bit of dynamic force going on as the load moves around.
那么当负载移动时 就会有一点动态力的作用
But eventually the cable appears to just pull out of its socket.
但最终线缆似乎只是被拉出其插座
I mean you can see in this frame there's like one or two wires that are still there.
我是指 在这帧画面中 还保持着一两个线缆
but everything else is moving to the left under the tension.
但其他所有的东西都在拉力的作用下向左移动
So what happens at the end of these cables is
那么这些线缆的末端是这么固定的
they take all the wires and they spread them out into a wide bundle
他们把所有钢丝散开捆成一束
and put that inside like a cup shaped socket.
然后把它放在杯状的插座里面
Then they pour zinc inside that
然后他们把锌倒进去
and the zinc of course sets and that way you have essentially a solid metal blob at the end.
而锌就会嵌进去 这样一来 线缆的末端就形成了一个实心的金属球
And of course that's what's on the other side of the saddle being held in by this structure.
当然 在鞍座的另一侧 线缆也是被这个结构固定住的
So now that load is being released.
那么现在这个负载被释放了
You've got even more dynamic redistribution of load between the other cables
其他线缆就得到了更多的动态负载
and they're now handling a static load would be twice what they're supposed to handle.
而这些线缆现在所承受的静态负载会是设计上的两倍
Of course dynamic loads are going to be even higher
当然 动态负载会更高
and if you look the cable behind it is already starting to come apart and it is going to snap.
而且如果你看后面的线缆就会发现 它已经开始散开了 要断了
But watch the cable nearest us that it's nice and clean and white
但是你看离我们最近的那根线缆 它又白又净又好
but as it becomes the main load-bearing object
但由于它成为了主要的承重对象
just watch all those wires snapping inside of this very very quickly.
现在就能看到这里面的线缆在非常快速地断裂
It had been doing such a good job up until this moment but it was more than it was designed for
在这之前 这跟线缆工作得很正常 但现在这样的负载已经超出了它的设计
and now it parts ways and at this point all the main cables have snapped
现在它分离了 这时所有的主线缆都断了
and the platform is beginning to fall down under the force of gravity.
而平台在重力的作用下开始往下掉
You can also notice by the way the previously broken cable.
顺便 你也可以发现 之前断裂的线缆(导致)
The socket has now been pushed out the other side
现在插座已经被推到了另一边去了
and that those cables are sticking up over the top are now falling away down the back.
而那些从顶部伸出来的线缆现正从后面掉落
So as the drone backs away,
那么随着无人机的后退
the auxiliary cable at the bottom of the frame you can see it wobbling and falling down.
框架底部的辅助线缆 你可以看到正它摇摇晃晃地往下掉
The cable at the top is still trying to support the wave guide and the catwalk
顶部的线缆还在努力支撑着波段和天桥
but that is gonna end up getting hit.
但这跟线缆最终也要完蛋
and so it snaps and you'll see a wave go into it.
那么它就断裂了 你会看到这跟线缆发生了波动
Now looks like it snaps from both ends because of a shock hitting that cable.
现在看来 它同时从两端折断 因为冲击力穿过了线缆
And that force is basically coming from the destruction of the catwalk.
而这股力量基本上来自于天桥的毁坏
You can see it at the top sort of in the curving across.
你可以看到它在顶部的弯曲交叉处
The cables from the platform are smashing through that and pulling the cable free.
平台上的线缆正在砸穿它 同时彻底脱落
So all that cabling is now falling towards the dish
那么所有的线缆现在都落到了碟型天线里
and you'll see the scars that it makes in the dish as it hits the surface.
而且在它落到表面的时候 你会看到它在天线里打出的伤痕
But also watch carefully on the left side, you can see the top two segments of the tower.
但也要仔细观察左侧 你可以看到塔的顶部两段
I believe that is like 150 feet, 45 meters worth of reinforced concrete falling down.
我觉得那差不多是150英尺 45米高的钢筋混凝土掉了下来
And equally as it pans across you can see a smaller chunk of tower number 12 falling down.
而同样的 当它平移过来的时候 你可以看到12号塔的一小块也在往下掉
So anyway I think that's all the important things to see from the drone footage.
那么无论如何 我想这是从无人机视频中可以看到的所有重要的东西
Let's switch over to the gopro footage from the control room.
让我们切换到控制室的Gopro视频
So again I'm going to run this at a quarter speed.
那么我还是要以四分之一的速度运行这段视频
So looking at the triangular platform,
那么 看着三角平台
you've got the curved azimuth arm hanging underneath it
其下挂着弯曲的方位臂
and that runs on a circular rail.
并运转在环形轨道上
Now as the platform begins to fall and get pulled sideways by the cable tension
那么 当平台开始下降并被线缆拉力拉到侧面时
this basically jumps off its rails and begins to fall down
整个平台脱轨而出 并开始下降
but it also does it with such aggression that if you watch as it fades below the bottom,
但这也是非常激烈的 如果你仔细观察 直到它消失在底部的话
it actually starts to bend and break.
你会发现 实际上它开始了弯曲并断裂
Simultaneously you can see the support cables for the platform
同时 你可以看到平台的支撑线缆
just smashing through the catwalk and the waveguide.
完全撞开了天桥和波导
And of course that's the force that causes the final cable to snap on the distant tower.
当然这也是导致最后一根缆绳在远处的塔上断裂的力量
The distant tower now begins to fall over
远处的塔现在开始倒下
because it has all the tension on those backstay cables
因为它承受了所有后部线缆的拉力
that are used to keep the tower solid.
而这些线缆是用来保持塔身稳固的
Also now tower 12 comes down
另外现在12号塔也倒下来了
and you can get an idea for the scale of this
这规模有多大
by seeing the platforms and ladders that are attached to the end of this thing.
你看看这座塔末端的平台和梯子就知道了
Again this is a horrendously dangerous place to be right now.
现在 这又是一个可怕而危险的地方
Those cables would be lethal if you were hit by one.
如果你被线缆击中 这将是致命的
So again we're really lucky that nobody was injured during this very violent event.
那么再说一下 很幸运 没有人在这次非常暴力的事件中受伤
So anyway after the dust settled, a bunch of journalists were publishing photos
那么无论如何 尘埃落定后  一群记者发布了照片
and these were the best photos I saw from it.
而这些是我看到的最好的照片
This is by Juan Costa of Noticel.
这是由NotiCel报社的Juan Costa拍摄的
He actually early on and after Arecibo's first cable failure.
他其实早在和阿雷西博的第一次线缆故障后
He emailed me a bunch of links saying trying to help me give me clues on what I should cover.
就在邮件里给我发了一堆链接 说想提示我该报导些什么
These are the concrete towers.
这些是混凝土塔
You can see the rebar sticking up there.
你可以看到钢筋从其上伸出
I don't think these are up to modern standards to be honest.
说实话 我觉得这些都不符合现代标准
And that's the triangular remains of the platform
那么这就是平台的三角形遗迹
which was just thrown hard against the side of this hole
刚好被狠狠地扔在这个洞的旁边
essentially like a slingshot.
基本上就像一个弹弓
The conference center and a bunch of other buildings were seriously damaged by falling cables.
会议中心和其他一堆建筑被掉落的线缆严重损坏
Some can be repaired. Some will have to be demolished and rebuilt.
有些可以修复 有些将不得不被拆除和重建
But even before the cleanup can start they're going to have to clear roads.
但即使在清理工作开始之前 他们也要清理道路
This is a tower number eight.
这是八号塔
The top of this has basically blocked one of the access roads.
这座塔的顶部已经基本堵住了其中一条通道
There will be a massive cleanup operation for months to come.
在未来的几个月 会进行大规模的清理
And I would love to think that in the future,
而我很想知道 在未来
there is the will and the money to rebuild something in this space
在这个领域 会有意愿和资金重建
that is comparable and as functional and as important to not just the scientific community
一些在功能性和重要性上可与之相比的东西 而且不仅对科学界非常重要
but to the local populace who saw this as a an important part of their island.
但对当地居民来说也是如此 他们认为这是他们岛屿的一个重要部分
There are of course petitions already being set up
当然 他们已经安排上了一些请愿
to try and put some political pressure on various people to make something happen.
来尝试给不同的人施加一些魄力提叩压力 让他们有所行动
Again I think the National Science Foundation have pretty much said.
同样我认为基本上NSF也都说过了
There is a standard process for bidding and proposing such contracts
提出并竞标这样的合同有一个标准的程序
which is sort of code speak for if something comes up with this sufficient merits it might be considered
这基本就是套话 意思是如果有什么带有充分优点的项目 则会被考虑
but equally I think that big projects like this are very much driven by politics.
但我同样认为 在很大程度上 像这样的大项目是由魄力提克斯驱动的
And in that front Puerto Rico has a problem
而在这方面 波多黎各不太行
because it doesn't get the same representation as the states in the United States.
因为它在美国国内并没有获得和州同等的代表地位
But as a site for future projects, the existing site has many advantages.
但作为未来项目的选址 现有的场地有很多优势
It's already gone through a lot of the environmental impact requirements.
它已经通过了很多环境影响的规定
It has the radio quiet zones already figured out.
它的无线电寂静区已经被确定下来了
And perhaps most importantly there's a bunch of local people that have already worked on such.
而且也许最重要的是有一群当地人已经在做这样的工作
They've grown up with this telescope
他们是和这个望远镜一起成长起来的
and they understand how to make something of this magnitude work.
他们懂得如何让这种规模的东西工作
I really hope that we will be looking forward in a few years time to what will be on this site
我真的希望 几年后我们会期待着这个地方的未来
as opposed to merely looking back at what was on this site.
而不是仅仅回顾一下这个地方的过去
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全